<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ben Does Baseball</title>
    <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ben Does Baseball</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 20:50:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://baseball.benbailey.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Starters Who Can&#39;t Finish What They Started</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/04/starters-cant-finish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 20:50:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/04/starters-cant-finish/</guid>
      <description>Some starters can&amp;rsquo;t finish innings. More specifically, some starters are pretty good at getting two outs, but much worse at getting the third. In looking at potential ways to identify starters who may work better as relievers, I came across Baseball Reference&amp;rsquo;s number of outs splits. To find good candidates for this analysis, I looked at Fangraphs&amp;rsquo; splits leaderboard for worst ERA with two outs. I took the top (or bottom) three pitchers with more than 30 IP: Tyler Duffey, Anibal Sanchez, and Michael Pineda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kris Bryant Loves the Reds</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/04/kris-bryant-reds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 18:48:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/04/kris-bryant-reds/</guid>
      <description>Kris Bryant was very good last year. The Reds were&amp;hellip;not great last year. In fact, the Reds&amp;rsquo; bullpen was historically bad. Early in the season they set a record for consecutive games allowing at least one run, and later in the season they set a record for home runs allowed.
Kris Bryant, of course, was the National League MVP.
This is what the MVP did against normal pitching in 699 plate appearances:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing Starter Performance by Inning</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/starters-through-innings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 23:15:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/starters-through-innings/</guid>
      <description>In an attempt to sharpen my data visualization skills, I decided to look at some of the top starters from the 2016 season by inning. The pitchers were selected by a combination of innings pitched, complete games, and personal preference. Each pitcher pitched at least 150 innings last season. One thing to keep in mind with all of these is that as the game goes on the sample size decreases. Starters rarely made it through the ninth inning this season, so later game results should be taken with a grain of salt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carl Edwards Had a Bad Day in a Great Year</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/carl-edwards-jr-bad-day-great-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 11:48:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/carl-edwards-jr-bad-day-great-year/</guid>
      <description>This post was featured on the Fangraphs community blog here
This week I played around with the baseballr package, which provides easy access to FanGraphs, Baseball Reference, and Statcast data in R1.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been particularly intrigued recently by Carl Edwards Jr., a Cubs reliever who got called up last season. He had always seemed to be surprisingly good, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware quite how good he was until I calculated wOBA allowed by pitchers in 2016 and found that he had the third lowest in the league, behind only Kenley Jansen and Zach Britton, and in front of Clayton Kershaw, Aroldis Chapman, and Andrew Miller.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Events and Dynamic UI</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/events-and-dynamic-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 12:46:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/03/events-and-dynamic-ui/</guid>
      <description>This week I focused on improving the usability of the Shiny app. I used Shiny&amp;rsquo;s renderUI function to dynamically generate the options for the game select dropdown. I also set up a baseball API here, and added another API endpoint to get the list of games that happened on any given day.
One of the nicer things I added to the Shiny app was the use of the tryCatch function to hide confusing error messages from the user, like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An App!</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/02/an-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 18:45:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/02/an-app/</guid>
      <description>This week I made a Shiny interface to the win probability and description services. It can be viewed here. To do this, I had to set up hosting for both Shiny and my Elixir backend service. I also switched from embedding/posting the plots on Plotly to embedding them in the new Shiny application, which should help reduce costs. Learning more about Shiny made implementing the interface relatively simple. The generation of the graphs is now abstracted into a function that grabs JSON data from the API server I set up, which makes it much easier to generate graphs for any desired game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schedule</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 18:54:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/schedule/</guid>
      <description> 2017-02-14
 Set up blog Look into win probability calculation Make a nice probability graph  2017-02-21
 Create Shiny app Move graphs to Shiny Automate creation of graphs Set up hosting  2017-03-03
 Improve Shiny UI Improve Shiny UX Add API endpoints to support the above improvements  2017-03-22
 Research win probability modeling Play around with baseballr package Practice more specific analysis  2017-03-29
 Modeling pitcher performance by inning Combining ggplot plots   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptions and Probabilities</title>
      <link>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/02/descriptions-and-probabilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 18:38:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://baseball.benbailey.me/2017/02/descriptions-and-probabilities/</guid>
      <description>This week I mostly focused on experimenting with the Retrosheet and MLB Gameday API formats. Using the baseball umbrella application combined with R and Plotly, I generated a win expectancy graph for a random game.
In any given situation, the win expectancy is equivalent to the percentage of games that teams in that exact situation went on to win. To calculate the win probability of a situation, the application converts the situation into a hash using the number of outs, inning, number and position of base runners, and the current score, then looks it up in a table of historical win probabilities.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>